<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The terrible and deserued death of Francis Rauilliack shewing the manner of his strange torments at his execution, vpon Fryday the 25. of May last past, for the murther of the late French King, Henry the fourth. Together with an abstract out of diuers proclamations, and edicts, now concerning the state of France. As it was printed in French in three seuerall bookes published by authoritie. 1610.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1610</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 16 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 10 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10476</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20755</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105057</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840787</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840787</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5318</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10476)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5318)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 904:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The terrible and deserued death of Francis Rauilliack shewing the manner of his strange torments at his execution, vpon Fryday the 25. of May last past, for the murther of the late French King, Henry the fourth. Together with an abstract out of diuers proclamations, and edicts, now concerning the state of France. As it was printed in French in three seuerall bookes published by authoritie. 1610.</title>
                  <author>R. E., fl. 1610.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by R. Blower and E. Allde] for William Barley, and Iohn Baylie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1610.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Turned into English by R.E."--p.16.</note>
                  <note>Printers' names from STC.</note>
                  <note>Blower printed the 1st quire, Allde the rest--STC.</note>
                  <note>Print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ravaillac, François, 1578-1610 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5318:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TERRIBLE AND DESER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued death of Francis Rauilliack, ſhewing the manner of his ſtrange torments at this Execution, vpon Fryday the 25. of May laſt paſt, for the murther of the late French King, Henry the fourth.</p>
            <p>TOGETHER WITH AN ABSTRACT Out of diuers Proclamations, and Edicts, now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ſtate of France.</p>
            <p>As it was Printed in French in three ſeuerall Bookes publiſhed by Authoritie. 1610.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the quartering of Francis Ravilliack</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>At London printed for William Barley. and Iohn Bayhe. 1610.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_an_execution">
            <pb facs="tcp:5318:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:5318:2"/>
            <head>The true maner of the ſtrange execution of <hi>Francis Ranilliack</hi> (for the late murther of the French King, <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth) who was tormented to death, vpon a ſkaffould, in the Cittie of <hi>Paris</hi> the 25 of May laſt 1610.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE moſt Inhumaine</hi> murther lately comitted vpon the perſon of the late French King, Henry the fourth of famous memory, hath much diſquieted the ſtate of Fraunce, and ſo buſyed other kingdoms, in hunting after the true reports thereof, ſo fare forth, that we thinke it an in terior loue to our countri-men to haue an abſtract of the moſt accurences that happened ſince that vnnaturall accydent, and fiirſtto begin with the viperous homicyde the bludie actor of this deede, who ſtroue with the enuy of his hart
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:5318:3"/>draw in pieces the bowells that cheriſhed his life. (floriſhing Fraunce I meane) that proues abortiue, in bringing forth ſuch an vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall french-man.</p>
            <p>This paracide, <hi>Frances Rauilliack,</hi> in time paſt of the order of the Felician fryers, but of late a practiſſioner in the lawe (by ſome named a pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty fogger) borne in the towne of <hi>Angoleſme,</hi> a place not fare diſtant from the Citty of <hi>Paris,</hi> who after he had vnluckedly accompliſhed this bloody ſtratagem, by taking away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> preſeruer of ſo many liues, was vpon the 23 of May laſt, araingned, conuicted, and condempued by due order of law, in the great court and chamber of <hi>Turnella</hi> in <hi>Paris,</hi> before all the Aſſembli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Preſidents, Councellors, and Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners, at the Requeſt of <hi>Du Viquit,</hi> Aturney generall to the King, whoſe place &amp; authority was there then to inquire againſt this <hi>Francis Rauilliack,</hi> for the murther of his late ſoueraigne, Henry the fourth King of Fraunce and Nauare, where-vppon, this <hi>Francis Rauilliack,</hi> with a ſad &amp; deathlike countenance, holding vp his guilty hand before this great aſſembly, preſently confeſſed guilty, and that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:5318:3"/>he became this his countries ſhame, onely by the inſtigation of the deuill, and not any other accomplices, &amp; confederats would he reueale, but in a Satanicall maner vowed himſelfe to ſecrecie, wherevpon the law proceeded, and a moſt terrible ſentence of death pronounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him there, according to a generall decree of that great court of parliament, &amp; ſo being a condemned Uillaine was with a ſtrong gard of armed men conuayd to priſon, otherwiſe by the violent rage of the common people, he had beene torne in peeces, ſuch was the loue they bore to their late King.</p>
            <p>Upon the Fryday following, being the 25. of May, (according to their computation) this <hi>Frauces Rauilliack</hi> was in a moſt vile and bace manner caried to execution as followeth.</p>
            <p>Firſt, (naked in his ſhirt) he was brought out of the <hi>Conſergery,</hi> (being the priſon for the palace) with a lighted Tortch of two pownd waight i none hand, and the Knife (wherewith he killed the King) chained to the other hand, ſo openly to be ſeene, that the leaſt childe there preſent might behold it, after this, he was placed ſtanding vpright in a tumbrell or dung<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cart
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:5318:4"/>Duug-cart, and ſo from thence, conducted with a gard of Cittizens to the Capitall church in <hi>Paris,</hi> where being adiudged to do penance he had bene made a ſacrafize to the rage of the rude people, had not (there bin apoynted Officers to ſee his execution) preuinted it.</p>
            <p>After this, being accompanied to the place of execution with two doctors of diuinitie, all the way perſwading him to ſaue his ſoule from euerlaſting puniſhment, by reuealing and laying oppen his Aſſocyates therein, which he would not, but ſtiffly (though vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graciouſly) tooke the bloody burthen vpon his owne ſhoulders, withſtanding, euen to the death, all faire promiſes whatſoeuer. In this manner as I ſayd before, was he caried to the Greue, being a ſpatious ſtreete, and about the middle of <hi>Paris,</hi> where was builded a very ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanciall ſcaffould of ſtrong timber, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon, according to his Iudgment he was to be tormented to death: <hi>Du Viquit</hi> the Kings Aturny generall was apoynted principall to ſee the execution, and there to gather (if he
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:5318:4"/>could) ſome further light of this vnchriſtian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like conſpiracie.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of the quartering of Francis Ravilliack</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>But ſo ſtrongly was his fleſh and ioynts knit together, that of long time, theſe foure horſes could not diſmember him, nor any way teare one ioynt from the other, ſo that one of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:5318:6"/>the horſes faynted, the which a Marchant of the Citty of Paris perceiuing, put to one of his owne, being a horſe of an exceeding great ſtrength, yet notwitſtanding for all this, they were conſtrained to cut the fleſh vnder, his armes and thighes with a ſharp rayſor, by which meanes his body was the eaſier torne in peeces: which being done, the rage of the people grew ſo violent, that they ſnatched the diſmembred carcaſſe out of the executioners hands, ſome beate it in ſunder againſt the ground, others cut it in peices with kniues, ſo that there was nothing leſt but boanes, which were brought to the place of execution and there burned to cinders, the aſhes wherof was ſcattered into thewind, as being thought to be vnworthie of the earths buriall. God in his Iuſtice I will hope in the like manner reward all ſuch as repine at their countries ſafety, and deſperatly attempt to lift their hands againſt Gods anointed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:5318:6"/>
            <head>THE BREFES TAKEN OF DIVERS EDICTS AND DECREES lately proclaimed in France in this place.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EWES the 13. by the grace of God, King of France and Nauarre,</signed>
               <salute>to all his louing ſubiects, health:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHereas the inhumaine murther of our late deceaſed Father, HENRY the fourth of famous memory, is as farre as Law and Iuſtice can reach vnto, reuenged vpon the body of that parracide <hi>Francis Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaillac,</hi> whoſe death ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly witneſſeth, and now ſtands regeſterd and example of ſeuerity in ſuch a cauſe, yet nature and duty bindeth vs to add this further vnto it: we therefore by the aduiſe of our foure Courts of Parliament, the Lords thereof, ſpirituall &amp; temporall that all the lands, goods, and cattels late belonging
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5318:7"/>to the aforeſaid traytor <hi>Francis Rauaillac,</hi> ſhall be confiſcate to our vſe, and alſo the houſe in <hi>Angoleſm<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> wherein he was borne, to be vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ruinated, and be conuerted into a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon leaſtall, and in the ſame place neuer any more houſe to be built: Alſo we by our autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity do decree and ordaine, iudge, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, that the Father and Mother of the ſaid <hi>Francis Rauaillac,</hi> be for euer baniſhed our Kingdome of France, and all the Prouinces belonging therunto, not to beſeene after the date of ſeauenteen dayes be expiered, neuer to returne vpon paine of hanging: Alſo we or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daine, that the vncles, brothers, ſiſters and all his kindred, ſhall neuer more take vpon them the name of <hi>Rauaillac,</hi> but take to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues ſome other name, vpon the like paine of puniſhment, as a name, vnworthy of our countrye. All which we doe commaund to be proclaimed throughout all our Prouinces, by the ſound of tro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pet as the order is. For the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution of which buſines, we do giue full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to <hi>du Vicquet,</hi> our Atorney Generall. Dated at our Palace in <hi>Paris</hi> the 29. of May 1610. and ſigned with the great ſeale of yellow wax, by the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>POTIER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters_patent">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:5318:7"/>
            <head>A BRIEF OF LETTERS PAT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TENTS GIVEN TO the Queene.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>EWES the 13. by the grace of God, King of France and Nauarre, &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To our friends and faithfull Councellors of our Court of Parliament of Roan, health:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>LOOKING to the neceſſity of the time, and for the maintenance of the ſtate in peace, vpon the miſerable accident committed vpon the perſon of our moſt Royall King and Father, and being in our minority, we doe eſtabliſh and make this good order for the preſeruation of our louing ſubiects, to liue in the vnion and concord as they did in the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:5318:8"/>time of our Father, and as by the Councell of our Royall Mother, Princes of our blood, other Princes, Prelats, Dukes, Peeres, and Officers of the Crowne, we are tranſported to this our Parliament of Paris, and being ſeated in our ſeate of Iuſtice, we do fully yeeld our whole gouernment to our Mother, to haue care of vs, and protect vs till we come to age, not ſuffering any coſtome to be denyed, but all things to be performed, and continued in as good force, as they did in our Fathers time to the quiet of our land, and the peace of our louing ſubiects: giuen at our Palace in Paris the 18. of may 1610. and of our raigne the firſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>SEene, publiſhed, and regiſtered in Court by <hi>du Vicquet,</hi> Attorney General, <date>the aforeſayed 18, of May,</date> Signed likewiſe by <hi>de Boyleueſque,</hi> Secretary to the Parliament of Roan, and proclamed in euery Prouince, that none here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall pretend cauſe of ignorance.</dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letters_patent">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:5318:8"/>
            <head>By the King.</head>
            <opener>
               <signed>LEWS the 13. by the grace of God King of France and Nauarre &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To all our louing ſubiects to whome theſe ſhall appertayne: health,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Since the vnhapie murther of our late fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: The Queene our royall mother now Regent ouer vs, hauing teares in her eyes and ſorrowe in her heart, hath not let to worke with great magnanimitie and proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence for this vnnaturall accident, that it might not be preiudiciall to our perſon, our Kingdome, nor to our ſubiects, knowing her ſelfe obliged to that duty, not onely for the naturall affection ſhe beares vs, but being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared Regent, and loaden with the affaires of the Kingdome, by the wils and authority of the Princes of our blood and others of the Parliament, wee leauing of hte ſeate of Iuſtice, by which meanes her paines is great and ſo happie, to our ſubiects nere vs and our Cittie of <hi>Paris</hi> deſiring no deuty to vs, but to our honored Lady and mother, for which we doe not doubt of your willingnes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:5318:9"/>in ſo doing, we ſhall giue you thankes with our loue.</p>
            <p>Furthermore, conſidering that in the times paſtm the daies of our late father, and other Kings his predeceſſors, that neither of theſe two Religions (by vs now tollerated) could not be weeded out of the Kingdome without much blood ſhed: be it now therefore ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and likewiſe we doe alowe both the ſame through all our Prouinces, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction as it was in our fathers time, and the hinderers thereof to be highly puniſhed.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Giuen at our Palace in <hi>Paris</hi> 
                  <date>the 22. of May,</date> and ſigned with the great Seale in yellow wax:</dateline> Farwell.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="summary_of_letters_patent">
            <head>Letters Patents of the King concerning the Edict of Nantes.</head>
            <p>VPon the 22. of May there wee Letters Patents granted, by proclamation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the will and intention of the King, for the intertainement of the Edict made in <hi>Nantes,</hi> concerning articles giuen to his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects profeſſing the pretended reformed Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:5318:9"/>publiſhed in the Parliament at <hi>Roane</hi> the <hi>28.</hi> of Day <hi>1610.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Vpon Sunday their <hi>27</hi> of Day were nine thouſand Proteſtants at Church together verie peaceably, God be prayſed.</p>
            <p>The king is continually guarded with two hundred horſe, and his Swiſſers, beſids the Nobilitie which mourne greatly.</p>
            <p>The Duke <hi>de Neuers</hi> by aduice is retour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from the armie.</p>
            <p>The humdred thouſand men promiſed to the Marques of <hi>Brandenburgh</hi> doe remaine as they did before, and all the army beſides are well.</p>
            <p>Theſe bee the onely laſt and true newes out of <hi>France,</hi> take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of three ſeueral books there imprinted, the one at Roan, by Nartin Meſgiſſier Printer ordinary to the King,</p>
            <p>Another by Peter Courant according to the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:5318:10"/>coppy printed at Paris, by Anthony Vitray, by permiſſion of the Court.</p>
            <p>And another printed at Roan by the ſame Man, &amp; now an abſtract of them all turned into Engliſh by <hi>R. E.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer type="illustration">
               <figure/>
            </trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:5318:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
